<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Latest News | Wonders of Water Lab</title><link>https://wow-uh.github.io/post/</link><atom:link href="https://wow-uh.github.io/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><description>Latest News</description><generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><image><url>https://wow-uh.github.io/media/icon_hu66d27845b76c41767cc7b18b1be83d84_179348_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url><title>Latest News</title><link>https://wow-uh.github.io/post/</link></image><item><title>Taher to hold a Cyberinfrastructure Workshop at AWRA</title><link>https://wow-uh.github.io/post/2022-04-07-taher-awra/</link><pubDate>Sun, 08 May 2022 09:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://wow-uh.github.io/post/2022-04-07-taher-awra/</guid><description>&lt;p>Taher and two of his peers will be holding a workshop at the &lt;em>2022 Geospatial Water
Technology Conference&lt;/em>, held by American Water Resources Association (AWRA), in Austin, TX.
This one-day workshop is titled &amp;ldquo;&lt;em>R and Python Tools for Geospatial Water Applications Workshop&lt;/em>&amp;rdquo;
and will be held on May, 8th, 2022.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>More information about the workshop and registration can be found
&lt;a href="https://www.awra.org/Members/Events_and_Education/Events/2022_GIS_Conference/2022_GWTC_Workshops.aspx" target="_blank" rel="noopener">here&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="abstract">Abstract&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>This session and coupled workshop will cover a suite of free and open-source geospatial water data access and manipulation tools in both the python and R programming languages. The session will provide a high-level overview of packages and their capabilities using example applications as context and background. The workshop will be a hands-on opportunity to use the packages for sample applications and to interact with the package authors.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Taher published his paper at JAWRA</title><link>https://wow-uh.github.io/post/2022-01-10-taher-jawra-coastal/</link><pubDate>Mon, 10 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://wow-uh.github.io/post/2022-01-10-taher-jawra-coastal/</guid><description>&lt;p>Congratulations to Taher Chegini for publishing his paper in the Journal of the American Water Resources Association titled &amp;ldquo;A Novel Framework for Parametric Analysis of Coastal Transition Zone Modeling&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="abstract">Abstract&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Vulnerability of coastal regions to extreme events motivates an operational coupled inland-coastal modeling strategy focusing on the coastal transition zone (CTZ), an area between the coast and upland river. To tackle this challenge, we propose a top-down framework for investigating the contribution of different processes to the hydrodynamics of CTZs with various geometrical shapes, different physical properties, and under several forcing conditions. We further propose a novel method, called tidal vanishing point (TVP), for delineating the extent of CTZs through the upland. We demonstrate the applicability of our framework over the United States East and Gulf coasts. We categorize CTZs in the region into three classes, namely, without estuary (direct river–coast connection), triangular-, and trapezoidal-shaped estuary. The results show that although semidiurnal tidal constituents are dominant in most cases, diurnal tidal constituents become more prevalent in the river segment as the discharge increases. Also, decreasing the bed roughness value promotes more significant changes in the results than increasing it by the same value. Additionally, the estuary promotes tidal energy attenuation and consequently decreases the reach of tidal signals through the upland. The proposed framework is generic and extensible to any coastal region.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Guta published his paper at WRR</title><link>https://wow-uh.github.io/post/2022-01-10-guta-wrr-horton/</link><pubDate>Wed, 02 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://wow-uh.github.io/post/2022-01-10-guta-wrr-horton/</guid><description>&lt;p>Congratulations to Guta Abeshu for publishing his paper at Water Resources Research, titled &amp;ldquo;Horton Index: Conceptual Framework for Exploring Multi-Scale Links Between Catchment Water Balance and Vegetation Dynamics&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="abstract">Abstract&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>This paper is motivated to understand the multi-temporal scale characteristics of Horton Index (HI), an indicator of catchment-scale plant water use defined as the ratio of catchment vaporization (total evapotranspiration) to catchment wetting (precipitation minus surface runoff). Based on the generalized proportionality hypothesis, we first develop an analytical framework of HI applicable at multi-temporal scales as a single function of ecological aridity index (EAI), defined as the ratio of potential evapotranspiration to catchment wetting. We successfully validate this framework at the long-term, annual, and monthly scales at 343 natural catchments over the conterminous United States under varying climate and vegetation regimes. We show that vegetation plays an important role in regulating not only the partitioning of catchment wetting into vertical vaporization and horizontal baseflow, but also further partitioning of vaporization into initial and continuing components. Aided by this framework, we reveal emergent space-time similarity patterns between HI’s spatial (inter-catchment, regional) and temporal (within-catchment, inter and intra-annual) variability. On the one hand, HI increases with EAI, both spatially and temporally, following similar trends predicted by the analytical framework. On the other hand, the slopes of HI ∼ EAI relationships, denoted as d (HI)/d (EAI), decreased with EAI both spatially and temporally and, again, following similar trends suggested by the analytical framework. These findings suggest the promising potential of Horton Index as a conceptual yet quantitative framework for improving understanding and modeling of multi-scale ecological and hydrological processes and their interactions.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Guta published his paper at ESSD</title><link>https://wow-uh.github.io/post/2022-02-10-guta-essd-d50/</link><pubDate>Mon, 24 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://wow-uh.github.io/post/2022-02-10-guta-essd-d50/</guid><description>&lt;p>Congratulations to Guta Abeshu for publishing his paper at Earth System Science Data, titled &amp;ldquo;Median bed-material sediment particle size across rivers in the contiguous US&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="abstract">Abstract&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Bed-material sediment particle size data, particularly the median sediment particle size (D50), are critical for understanding and modeling riverine sediment transport. However, sediment particle size observations are primarily available at individual sites. Large-scale modeling and assessment of riverine sediment transport are limited by the lack of continuous regional maps of bed-material sediment particle size. We hence present a map of D50 over the contiguous US in a vector format that corresponds to approximately 2.7 million river segments (i.e., flowlines) in the National Hydrography Dataset Plus (NHDPlus) dataset. We develop the map in four steps: (1) collect and process the observed D50 data from 2577 U.S. Geological Survey stations or U.S. Army Corps of Engineers sampling locations; (2) collocate these data with the NHDPlus flowlines based on their geographic locations, resulting in 1691 flowlines with collocated D50 values; (3) develop a predictive model using the eXtreme Gradient Boosting (XGBoost) machine learning method based on the observed D50 data and the corresponding climate, hydrology, geology, and other attributes retrieved from the NHDPlus dataset; and (4) estimate the D50 values for flowlines without observations using the XGBoost predictive model. We expect this map to be useful for various purposes, such as research in large-scale river sediment transport using model- and data-driven approaches, teaching environmental and earth system sciences, planning and managing floodplain zones, etc. The map is available at &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4921987" target="_blank" rel="noopener">https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4921987&lt;/a> (Li et al., 2021a).&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Our sediment modeling paper was published at HESS</title><link>https://wow-uh.github.io/post/2022-02-10-hongyi-hess-mosart-sediment/</link><pubDate>Mon, 24 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://wow-uh.github.io/post/2022-02-10-hongyi-hess-mosart-sediment/</guid><description>&lt;p>Our paper published in Hydrology and Earth System Sciences, titled &amp;ldquo;A new large-scale suspended sediment model and its application over the United States&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="abstract">Abstract&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Suspended sediment plays a vital role in the regional and global cycling of carbon and nutrients by carrying carbon and nutrients from headwaters into lowland rivers and the oceans. Sediment transport through river systems is often fundamentally modified by human activities such as reservoir management. However, a physically-based representation of sediment transport is still missing in most existing Earth system models (ESMs), which are essential tools for modeling and predicting Earth system changes. Here, we introduce a multi-process river sediment module for ESMs, which includes (1) hillslope soil erosion and sediment discharge into streams, (2) sediment transport processes through river networks, (3) reservoir operation based on the inflows from upstream areas and water demand from downstream areas, and (4) sediment trapping by reservoirs. All model parameters are estimated a priori without calibration. We apply this new sediment modeling framework to the contiguous United States and validate it against historical observations of monthly streamflow and sediment discharges at 35 river gauges. The model reasonably well captures the long-term balance and seasonal variations of suspended sediment in large river systems. Furthermore, our model results show that suspended sediment discharge in managed rivers is affected more by reservoirs&amp;rsquo; direct trapping of sediment particles than by their flow regulation. This new sediment module enables future modeling of the transportation and transformation of carbon and nutrients carried by the fine sediment along the river–ocean continuum to close the global carbon and nutrient cycles.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>