<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Models and Datasets | Wonders of Water Lab</title><link>https://wow-uh.github.io/models/</link><atom:link href="https://wow-uh.github.io/models/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><description>Models and Datasets</description><generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><image><url>https://wow-uh.github.io/media/icon_hu66d27845b76c41767cc7b18b1be83d84_179348_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url><title>Models and Datasets</title><link>https://wow-uh.github.io/models/</link></image><item><title>Model for Scale Adaptive River Transport (MOSART)</title><link>https://wow-uh.github.io/models/mosart/</link><pubDate>Wed, 27 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://wow-uh.github.io/models/mosart/</guid><description>&lt;p>A new physically based runoff routing model, called the Model for Scale Adaptive River Transport (MOSART), has been developed to be applicable across local, regional, and global scales. Within each spatial unit, surface runoff is first routed across hillslopes and then discharged along with subsurface runoff into a “tributary subnetwork” before entering the main channel. The spatial units are thus linked via routing through the main channel network, which is constructed in a scale-consistent way across different spatial resolutions. All model parameters are physically based, and only a small subset requires calibration. MOSART has been applied to the Columbia River basin at ⅙°, ⅛°, ¼°, and ½° spatial resolutions and was evaluated using naturalized or observed streamflow at a number of gauge stations. MOSART is compared to two other routing models widely used with land surface models, the River Transport Model (RTM) in the Community Land Model (CLM) and the Lohmann routing model, included as a postprocessor in the Variable Infiltration Capacity (VIC) model package, yielding consistent performance at multiple resolutions. MOSART is further evaluated using the channel velocities derived from field measurements or a hydraulic model at various locations and is shown to be capable of producing the seasonal variation and magnitude of channel velocities reasonably well at different resolutions. Moreover, the impacts of spatial resolution on model simulations are systematically examined at local and regional scales. Finally, the limitations of MOSART and future directions for improvements are discussed.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>National map of median bed-material sediment particle size</title><link>https://wow-uh.github.io/models/sediment/</link><pubDate>Wed, 27 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://wow-uh.github.io/models/sediment/</guid><description>&lt;p>Bed-material sediment particle size data, particularly the median sediment particle size (D50), are critical for understanding and modeling riverine sediment transport. However, sediment particle size observations are primarily available at individual sites. Large-scale modeling and assessment of riverine sediment transport are limited by the lack of continuous regional maps of bed-material sediment particle size. We hence present a map of D50 over the contiguous US in a vector format that corresponds to approximately 2.7 million river segments (i.e., flowlines) in the National Hydrography Dataset Plus (NHDPlus) dataset. We develop the map in four steps: (1) collect and process the observed D50 data from 2577 U.S. Geological Survey stations or U.S. Army Corps of Engineers sampling locations; (2) collocate these data with the NHDPlus flowlines based on their geographic locations, resulting in 1691 flowlines with collocated D50 values; (3) develop a predictive model using the eXtreme Gradient Boosting (XGBoost) machine learning method based on the observed D50 data and the corresponding climate, hydrology, geology, and other attributes retrieved from the NHDPlus dataset; and (4) estimate the D50 values for flowlines without observations using the XGBoost predictive model. We expect this map to be useful for various purposes, such as research in large-scale river sediment transport using model- and data-driven approaches, teaching environmental and earth system sciences, planning, and managing floodplain zones, etc. The map is available at &lt;a href="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4921987" target="_blank" rel="noopener">https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4921987&lt;/a> (Li et al., 2021a).&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>